Guide to the New York State College of Human Ecology honors theses, 1970-2017.
New York State College of Human Ecology honors theses, 1970-2015.
- Series XVI. Class of 2001
  - Human Development
    - "Family-Staff Relationships in End-of-Life Care in Nursing Homes," Linda Goodman, 2001 (Box 5)
    - "Cornell University Language Aquisition Labortory: Analyzing Spanish Natural Speech Data of Children," Adriana Alves, 2001 (Box 5)
    - "The Transference of Visual and Auditory Source Memories in Children," Caitlin Dunning, 2001 (Box 7)
    - "The Effects of Life Events on the Division of Household Labor, Depressive Affect, Marital Satisfaction, and Marital Conflict of Older Couples," Meghan Gillan, 2001 (Box 7)
    - "Low-level Blood Lead and Intelligence in 5 year-old Children: Evidence for a Non-linear Relationship," Todd Jusko, 2001 (Box 7)
    - "College Students' Attitudes Toward the Aged and the Aging Process," Annie Roth, 2001 (Box 7)
    - "Lead Exposure and Prefrontal Functioning in Early Childhood," Donna Santoro, 2001 (Box 7)
    - "The Relation of Temperature Variance and Thermal Comfort to Learned Helplessness in Children," Ilene West, 2001 (Box 7)
    - "The Factors Affecting Female Attorneys' Rate of Promotion," Jennifer Zanko, 2001 (Box 7)
    - "The Relationship Between Body Weight and Self-Esteem in College Women," Meghan Butryn, 2001 (Box 9)
    - "Factors Associated With Individuals' Plans To Relocate For Career Growth," Sarah Ka-wah Yeung, 2001 (9)
  - Policy Analysis and Management
    - "Explaining the "Liberalness" of State Child Care Policy A Statistical Analysis," Jill Tauber, 2001 (Box 4)
    - "An Evaluation of Stakeholder Expectations in the Monroe County Juvenile Drug Court," Yurij Oleh Pawluk, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Textiles and Apparel
    - "Mass Customization of Wedding Dresses on the Internet," Rita Pui Kee Choy, 2001 (Box 4)
- Series XVII. Class of 2002
  - "An Evaluation of Richness of Representation as it Pertains to Memory Monitoring: Can Young Children Monitor?" Courtney Berry, 2002 (Box 7)
  - "Psychosocial Mentoring and Adolescent Career Development: Fostering Personal and Social Development in the Workplace," Krista Beiswenger, 2002 (Box 7)
  - "The Role of the HOME Inventory in the Relation Between Blood Lead Levels and IQ," Jessica Benas, 2002 (Box 7)
  - "Low-Level Lead Exposure and Child Behavior Problems," Jessica Conser, 2002 (Box 7)
  - "Fighting For Success: The Impact of Professors on African-American Students' Struggle for Academic Achievement in Predominantly White Universities," Carrie Davies, 2002 (Box 7)
  - "Phenomenological Exploration of Religion and Interpersonal Forgiveness," David Lee, 2002 (Box 7)
  - "Cultural Conceptions: How Cornell Students Think About Work and Family," Erica Levin, 2002 (Box 7)
  - "A Social Perspective on the Drum in Zimbabwe," Erica Liberman, 2002 (Box 7)
  - "Affect Expression and Emotion Recognition in Children," Thomas Olino, 2002 (Box 7)
  - "Contextual Environment Interactions For Cognitive Development in Toddlers: A Pathway," Annie Rosenberg, 2002 (Box 7)
  - "Cholinergic Contributions to the Enduring Effect of Early Lead Exposure on Sustained Attention and Reactivity to Errors," Veraanong Srakhao, 2002 (Box 9)
  - "The Relationship Between Bem Sex-Role Inventory and System for the Multiple Level Observation of Groups Revisited: How Well do Sex-Roles and Gender Predict Small Group Behavior?" Suzanne Saufer, 2002 (Box 9)
  - "An Examination of Spontaneous Answers to Questions About the Natural World: Do Young Children Actually Possess A 'Teleological Bias,'" Elena Ershova, 2003 (Box 7)
  - "Sexual Abuse Encounters: A Risk Factor for Drug and Alcohol Abuse in Adolescent Females," Llana Kramer, 2003 (Box 8)
  - "Stress Exposure, Risk and Protective Factors, and Psychological Outcomes in Adolescents," Sarah Bufferd, 2003 (Box 8)
  - "Changes in Overt and Covert Attention, Measured via Steady-State Visual Evoked Potentials (SSVEPs)," Katy Devine, 2003 (Box 8)
  - "Individual Differences in Reasoning," Randi Dublin, 2003 (Box 8)
  - "Parenting Practices and Their Effects on the Development of African American Children," Michelle Finnegan, 2003 (Box 8)
  - "Movement Attention Coupling in Infants and Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder in Children," Allison Friedman, 2003 (Box 8)
  - "Reasoning about Explanations: How Explanations are Evaluated in Light of Disconfirming Evidence," Yoko Iwaki, 2003 (Box 8)
  - "Infants' Comprehension of Novel Words and Novel Gestures," Tara Kakaty, 2003 (Box 8)
  - "Production of Novel Words and Gestures in 8- to 22-Month Old Infants," Caryn Kerman, 2003 (Box 8)
  - "Violence as Adaptation? The Interactive Relationship between Adolescent Violence, Community Violence, and Well-Being," Robert Latzman, 2003 (Box 8)
  - "Examining the Role of Theory and Bias in Evaluating Information," Joseph Marasia, 2003 (Box 8)
  - "Religion as a Moderator of Stress and Well-Being Among Parents of Children with Autism," Sara Rosenblum, 2003 (Box 8)
  - "The Effects of Crowding and Perceived Crowding on Blood Pressure, Blood Pressure Reactivity and Recovery, and Neuroendocrine Markers: A Longitudinal Study," Dana Shanis, 2003 (Box 8)
  - "Cultural Themes in Dinnertime Conversations: A Qualitative Investigation," Kiran Sunkavalli, 2003 (Box 8)
  - "The Effects of Multiple Chronic Stressors on Cardiovascular Reactivity and Recovery In Children," Harris Tesher, 2003 (Box 8)
  - Design and Environmental Analysis
    - "A Look at the Impact of the Presence of a Community School on Neighborhood Members' Sense of a Community," Meredith Topper, 2002 (Box 4)
    - "Kitchen Design for the Elderly: Planning for Normal and Impaired Aging," Courtney R. Sherman, 2002 (Box 4)
    - "An Examination of Pilot Satisfaction with the Joint Helmet Mounted Cueing System," Melinda Jean McElheny, 2002 (Box 4)
  - Human Development
    - "Temperament and Suggestability in 3-5 Year Old Children," Heather Lord, 2002 (Box 9)
  - Policy Analysis and Management
    - "Financing Long-Term Care in the United States: The Role of Public-Private Partnerships," Lauren Hersch Nicholas, 2002 (Box 4)
    - "The Impact of Race-Related Preferences on Residential Search, Preference, and Choice," Meghan L. Morris, 2002 (Box 4)
    - "Movement Towards Market Efficiency?: An Analysis of Price Dispersion Between the Internet Market and the Ithaca Market," Michelle Steinberg, 2002 (Box 4)
  - Textiles and Apparel
    - "'Smart Systems:' Wearable Integration of Intelligent Technology," Lucy E. Dunne, 2002 (Box 4)
- Series XVIII. Class of 2003
  - Design and Environmental Analysis
    - "Measurement of Children's Environmental Attitudes and Behaviors," Rachel Stecker, 2003 (Box 5)
    - "The Usability Comparison of Two Touch Screen Point-of Sale (POS) System Platforms in Family Dining Restaurants," Mariah Levitt, 2003 (Box 5)
    - "Restorative Elements in Child Care Facilities: Effects on Behavior and Development in Preschool Children," Caroline Hegarty, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Division of Nutritional Sciences
    - "An Analysis of Song and Female Choice: Avian Brain Regions in Relation to Evolutionary Selection Factors," Debbie Weng, 2003 (Box 4)
  - Policy Analysis and Management
    - "Information Technology's New Role in the Healthcare Industry," Lora Gleicher, 2003 (Box 4)
    - "Profiling the Demand for Student Leadership Training Within the College of Human Ecology," Daniel Blake Levy, 2003 (Box 4)
    - "An Analysis of the Cable Industry from 1996 to 2001," David Reichenberg, 2003 (Box 4)
    - "The Effects of School Racial Composition on Academic Achievement in Adolescence," Hedwig Eugenie Lee, 2003 (Box 4)
    - "Courage and Despair in the Face of La Crisis: Middle-Class Argentines Tell Their Stories," Keren Lerner (Cornell Presidential Research Scholars Senior Project), 2003 (Box 9)
- Series XIX. Class of 2004
  - "Discrepant Perceptions of Parental Responsiveness in Mother-Adolescent Dyads and Psychological Distress in Adolescents," Corissa Lynn Callahan, 2004 (Box 8)
  - "The Effects of Gender and Motivation on Causal Reasoning," Kathryn Howell, 2004 (Box 8)
  - "Hospicare:An Assessment of Bereavement Services," Jason Kwartner, 2004 (Box 8)
  - "The Motivation to Disconfirm Can Be a Double-edged Sword," Victoria Liang, 2004 (Box 8)
  - "Elder Abuse: An Assessment of Mandatory Reporting Laws," Stacey Jennifer Lipitz, 2004 (Box 8)
  - "The Effect of the Mother-Child Relationship, Family Form, and Maternal Presence on Adolescent Drug Use in African American Families," Noah M. Meyers, 2004 (Box 8)
  - "Religious Conceptualization and Coping Strategies in College Students," Kimberly Ann Notheis, 2004 (Box 8)
  - "Gender, Extraversion, Life Events, and Depression," Jessica Richards, 2004 (Box 8)
  - "Some Anomalies are More Problematic than Others," Lindsay B. Slater, 2004 (Box 8)
  - "Personality Differences in Eyewitness Identification," Maryann Totino, 2004 (Box 8)
  - "Do Social Networks Provide a Buffer for the Effect of Stress on Psychological Distress? An Investigation of the Influence of Rural Mothers' Social Networks," Rachel Theresa Ziwich, 2004 (Box 8)
  - "An Experience Sampling Study of Stress and Coping Among Low and Middle-Income Youth," Nicole S. Simon, 2004 (Box 9)
  - Design and Environmental Analysis
    - "The Effects of Increased Technology Complexity and Reduced Staff Shift-Work on Visual and Mental Performance," Stephanie A. Thurston, 2004 (Box 5)
  - Human Development
    - "The Effectiveness of Second Step, A Violence Prevention Curriculum, In The Ithaca, New York Area", 2004 (Box 9)
    - "Arts Integration and Classroom Management Styles in the Binghamton City School District Elementary Schools," Rachel Wechsler, 2004 (Box 9)
  - Policy Analysis and Management
    - "Making the Grade: A Longitudinal Analysis of Education and Adult Obesity," Allison Cook, 2004 (Box 4)
    - "Women in Community Organizing: A Mixed Method Study of Women Leaders from the Northwest Bronx Community and Clergy Coalition," Ha My Vu, 2004 (Box 4)
    - "From Rx to OTC: An Analysis of the Changes in Flow, Format, and Content of Print Advertisements in the Smoking Cessation Pharmaceutical Industry," Michelle M. Crocco, 2004 (Box 4)
    - "Substitutability of Prescription Drug Benefits for Hospitalization and Emergency Room Visits," Robert A. Chu, 2004 (Box 4)
    - "The Establishment and Evolution of State-Mandated Testing," Anar K. Rathod, 2004 (Box 4)
- Series XX. Class of 2005
  - Design and Environmental Analysis
    - "Community Resources and Adolescent Planning Styles," Kate Davidoff, 2005 (Box 5)
  - Division of Nutritional Sciences
    - "Nutrition Knowledge of Cornell University Students: Nutrition knowledge, attitudes, and behaviors of nutrition and non-nutrition majors at Cornell University," Jessica Rachel Furst, 2005 (Box 4)
    - "Functional Characterization of a-Tocopherol Transfer Protein Ataxia with Vitamin E Deficient Mutants," Katrina Bernardo, 2005 (Box 10)
  - Policy Analysis and Management
    - "The Effect of the State of Israel's Education System on Peace Process Perceptions by Israeli Youth," Ari Nathan Stern, 2005 (Box 4)
    - "Explanations for the Link Between Body Weight and Labor Market Outcomes," Harris Ian Ziskroit, 2005 (Box 4)
    - "Diversity of Extracurricular Activities," Dominic E Frongillo, 2005 (Box 4)
    - "Does Market Capital Translate into Marital Capital?: A Comparison of Marital Homogamy Between Professional and Non-Professional Women Upon Remarriage," Parijat Sharma, 2005 (Box 4)
    - "The Effects of a Threat Level Change by the Department of Homeland Security on U.S. Airline and Defense Stocks," Michael Pandolfini, 2005 (Box 9)
    - "Child Protective Services Use of Precautionary Measures Against False Allegations"," Allison Nicole Lipitz, 2005 (Box 9)
  - Textiles and Apparel
    - "Understanding the Race/Class Gap in Academic Achievement," Sarah Elliot, 2005 (Box 4)
  - Human Development
    - "Maltreatment and Anti-Social Behavior: Understanding the Pathways of Resilience," Alana Siegel, 2005 (Box 9)
- Series XXI. Class of 2006
  - Design and Environmental Analysis
    - "Volumetric Deformation: A New Objective Measure to Study Chair Comfort Using 3D Body Scanning Technology," Anshu Agarwal, Online
  - Division of Nutritional Sciences
    - "Effects of Male Aggressive Behavior on Female Mate Choice in Japanese Quail, Coturnix Japonica," Elizabeth Riccardi, 2006; CD#303
    - "Escaping Food Insecurity: A Portrait of Several Rural New York Families Using Mixed-Methods Analysis," Megan Lent, 2006 (Box 9)
  - Human Development
    - "Individual Differences in the Development of Effortful Control in Preschoolers," Hanna Muenke, 2006; CD#302
    - "The Mediating Role of Preschool Play Behavior in the Relationship Between Poverty and First Grade Socioemotional Competence," Jennifer L. Rosenbaum, 2006; CD#304
    - "Subclinical Obsessive Compulsive Disorder and its Relation to Academic Achievement and Defensive Pessimism," Mark Celano, 2006; CD#305
    - "The Quality of Memory for Events that Alter Identity," Judith Katz, 2006; CD#306
    - "The Development of Executive Control: Behavioral and Neutral Activity in a Proposed Pediatric Stroop Task," Sarah LaVallee, 2006 (Box 9)
  - Textiles and Apparel
    - "Fashioning the Tourist: An Andean Travelers Wardrobe - A Study in Curatorial Practice," Alana Staiti, 2006 (Box 10)
- Series XXII. Class of 2007
  - "Health and the Persistence of Food Insecurity in Rural New York Families," Lindsay Elizabeth Petrovic, 2007 (Box 9)
  - "Community Violence, Child Maltreatment, and Children's Behavioral Problems: An Ecological Perspective," Nina Wong, 2007 (Box 10)
- Series XXIII. Class of 2008
  - Human Development
    - "Meta-conceptual Thinking and Positive Outcomes Among Youth in a Refuge Camp" Bethany Ojalehto, 2008 (Box 9)
    - "It's Always Good to Think About Yourself: Self-Evaluations of Performance are Associated with Higher Self-Esteem" Dara Poliskin, 2008 (Box 9)
- Series XXIV. Class of 2012
  - Human Development
    - "You Can't Handle the Truth: Gist Memory Leads to Predictable False Memory Effects with Age," Brittany Cohen, 2012 (Box 9)
    - "Turn to Learn: How Spatial Experience and Left-Right Language Matter in Spatial Cognition," Abbie Dinowitz, 2012 (Box 9)
    - "Barriers to Birth Control Use in College Women," Margaret Gichane, 2012 (Box 9)
  - Textiles and Apparel
    - "Ithaca Underground: How Dress is Used to Show Community," Audrey Sutton, 2012 (Box 10)
- Series XXV. Class of 2013
  - Human Development
    - "Be Afraid, Be Very Afraid: Predictive Effects of Fearful and Fatalistic Attitudes on Young Adult Risk Behavior," Julie Avrutine, 2013 (Box 10)
    - "Does Parenting Matter? Exploring the Link Among Poverty, Mental State Language, and Executive Function in Infancy," Marie Camerota, 2013 (Box 10)
    - "Examining Parental Role in Children's Concepts of Choice," Shelby Distenfeld, 2013 (Box 10)
    - "The Effect of Poverty on Maternal Responsiveness, Child Negative Affect, and Effortful Control," Maggie Diu, 2013 (Box 10)
    - "Willingness to Grant Accommodations to Individuals Labeled as Mentally Ill and Physically Ill," Natalie Finn, 2013 (Box 10)
    - "Integrating the Mind and Body: Uncovering the Relationship between Attention and Body Movement in Infants," Meera Menon, 2013 (Box 10)
    - "An Investigation of Perceived Family Warmth, Non-Suicidal Self-Injury (NSSI), and NSSI Recovery," Rebecca A. Morgan, 2013 (Box 10)
    - "Greater Connectivity is Associated with Greater Framing Bias: A Combined DTI and MRI Study," Zachary Nollet, 2013 (Box 10)
    - "Comparing the Diagnostic Validity of ASPD Preceded by Conduct Disorder with Adult-Only Antisocial Personality Disorder," Brittany Tusa, 2013 (Box 10)
  - Textiles and Apparel
    - "The Origin and Evolution of "Prep" and its Socioeconomic Relevance," Anu Lingala, 2013 (Box 10)
- Series XXVI. Class of 2014
  - Human Development
    - "Relationships Between Domestic Violence, Social Support, and Maternal Psychosocial and Behavioral Outcomes," Victoria Atzl, 2014 (Box 10)
    - "Linking Emotional Competence and Learning Spanish as a Second Language," Martina Azar, 2014 (Box 10)
    - "Impact of Trauma Exposure on Gray Matter Volume: Assessing the Role of Development," Elizabeth DuPre, 2014 (Box 10)
    - "Gender Congruity and Physical Attractiveness in Leadership Evaluation," Evelyn Fok, 2014 (Box 10)
    - "Young Children Use Statistical Sampling to Infer Their Own Preferences," Lara Gentilini, 2014 (Box 10)
    - "Developmental Differences in Spatial Transformation Ability During Infancy," Samantha Marfurt, 2013 (Box 10)
    - "An Examination of System-and Individual-Level Factors Which May Be Associated with the Urban- Rural Disparity in Hospice Utilization," Meghan McDarby, 2014 (Box 10)
- Series XXVII. Class of 2015
  - Human Development
    - "Developmental Differences in Spatial Categorization of Korean Infants," Yeo Jin Ahn, 2015 (Box 10)
    - "Influence of Aging on the Neural Correlates of Autobiographical Memory, Prospection, and Theory of Mind," Chelsea Brite, 2015 (Box 10)
    - "The Intergroup Dialogue Project's Impact on Student Attitudes and Behaviors Regarding Diversity and Inclusion," Katelyn Fletcher, 2015 (Box 10)
    - "Assessing Impulsivity and Risk in Emerging Adulthood," Zoe Amelia Katz, 2015 (Box 10)
    - "Home is Where We Are Together: Reunion Sex Assists the Restoration of Physiological Co-Regulation in Romantic Couples," Devin Massaro, 2015 (Box 10)
    - "Only Skin-Deep: Revising First Impressions of Faces," Brian Meagher, 2015 (Box 10)
    - "The Effect of Minimal Group Bias in Memory and Attitude Over Time," Grace Monks, 2015 (Box 10)
  - Fiber Science and Apparel Design
    - "Increased Conductivity of Electrospun Pedot:PSS Nanofibers and Core-Shell Pedot Microfibers," Ariana Levitt, 2015 (Box 10)
- Series XXVIII. Class of 2016
  - Human Development
    - "Critical Thinking and Decision-making in Modern Day Physicians," James Patrick Dunlea, 2016 (Box 10)
    - "Race and Conceptions of Intelligence: Exploring how College Students of Different Races may Differ in Their Ideas of Intelligence," Trenel Francis, 2016 (Box 10)
    - "Reflections as a Resource: Mitigating the Effects of Gender Macroaggressions," Misha Inniss-Thompson, 2016 (Box 10)
    - "The Neural Correlates of Language Processing: A Meta Analysis of AD and MCI Studies," Azraa Janmohamed, 2016 (Box 10)
    - "The Time Course of False Memory Processes," Aaron Wei-Feng Lee, 2016 (Box 10)
    - "Expected Outcomes of Co-Rumination in Emerging Adults," Kathleen McCormick, 2016 (Box 10)
    - "Evaluating the Maturational Disparity Hypothesis: Is there a Physical and Cognitive Mismatch in Early Maturing Girls," Taylor McGuire, 2016 (Box 10)
    - "The Effect of the Color Red on Sexual Attraction: Replication and Extension in People with Same-Sex Attraction," Paisley Terenzi, 2016 (Box 10)
- Series XXIX. Class of 2017
  - Human Development
    - "Localization of Oxytocin-Like Containing Neurons in the Highly Vocal Gulf Toadfish with Comparisons to Mammals," Anna Claire Fernandez, 2017 (Box 10)
    - "When was Your Earliest Memory and How Do You Remember More Accurately? Young Adults Postdating Early Childhood Memories," Angel Khuu, 2017 (Box 10)
    - "Individual Differences in Perspective Taking with Interactive Social Learning," Brian LaGrant, 2017 (Box 10)
    - "The Effect of Minimal Group Membership on Children's Susceptibility to Suggestive Questioning," Leona Marie Sharpstene, 2017 (Box 10)
    - "Racial and Ethnic Differences in Pain Self-Management Techniques Among Older Adults with Chronic Pain," Sharnendra Sidhu, 2017 (Box 10)
    - "Intrinsic Functional Connectivity of the Default Mode Network is Associated with Individual Differences in Social Cognition," Hsiang Ling Tsai, Amber Lockrow, R. Nathan Spreng, 2017 (Box 10)
    - "The Role of Autonomic Processes in Adaptive Memory," Deaven Winebrake, 2017 (Box 10)
  - Design and Environmental Analysis
    - "Designing Undesigned Interior Playscapes:Implications from Junk Playgrounds and Makerspaces," Sohyun Lee, 2017 (Box 10)